<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ml:Event status="Published" user-group="markups" xmlns:ml="http://developer.marklogic.com/site/internal" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <ml:title>Next Mark-UPS Meeting Wednesday, July 7th</ml:title>
  <ml:created>2010-07-04T18:53:53.934239-07:00</ml:created>
  <ml:last-updated>2010-07-04T19:12:55.263964-07:00</ml:last-updated>
  <ml:description>
    <p>MarkLogic User Participation Sessions (Mark-UPS) will be meeting on Wednesday July 7th at <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?oe=UTF-8&amp;gfns=1&amp;q=131+National+Business+Parkway,+Suite+100,+Annapolis+Junction,+MD+20701&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=131+National+Business+Pkwy+%23100,+Jessup,+MD+20701&amp;gl=us&amp;ei=wDwxTJ20FMyknwfb3ZHeAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=geocode_result&amp;ct=title&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CBMQ8gEwAA">131 National Business Parkway</a>, Suite 200.  Get to know others in the area and 
follow-up on the great MarkLogic user community experience.  Pizza and soda will be provided. Mark-UPS, is led by Telly 
Stroumbis (<a href="https://exchange.marklogic.com/owa/redir.aspx?C=b1da91859b524df4a99f8aab4b6b0599&amp;URL=mailto%3atelly.stroumbis%40boeing.com">telly.stroumbis@boeing.com</a>)
 of Boeing.</p>
<div>
</div>
<h3><strong>Presentation:</strong></h3>
<div>Clark Richey, Jr. will present a preview of MarkLogic's upcoming 4.2 release. This 
release is packed with numerous major new features including several 
features designed specifically for the Federal community. Please join us
 for this unique opportunity to learn more about
 this exciting upcoming release!</div>
<div>
</div>
<h3><strong>
Speaker Bio:</strong></h3>
<div>Clark Richey, Jr. is the Principal Technologist, Federal at MarkLogic 
where he works closely with customers to help them architect 
maintainable, scalable solutions to their business problems. He is 
active in the developer community, providing technology education
 and best practices for using MarkLogic efficiently while gathering 
developer feedback for future product enhancements.  Clark has spent 
more than ten years architecting and developing large scale systems for 
various government clients including the FBI, Department
 of Defense, Department of Labor, the Veterans Administration and 
various IC organizations.  He is also a Java Champion and an associate 
professor at Loyola University. Clark has a B.S. in Computer Science 
from U.M.U.C. and a Master's Degree in Computer Science
 from American University.</div>
<div>
 </div>
<div>
<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Please RSVP so that we can pre-print badges and know how much food to 
order</span>.</div>
<div>
 </div>
<div>
<strong>Note</strong>: advanced notice is required for non-U.S. Citizens.</div>
  </ml:description>
  <ml:details>
    <ml:date>2010-07-07</ml:date>
    <ml:time>5:30PM - 7:30PM</ml:time>
    <ml:location>131 National Business Parkway, Suite 100, Annapolis Junction, MD 20701 (visitors need to sign in at Suite 120, see link below for map)</ml:location>
    <ml:topic>MarkLogic Server 4.2 Preview</ml:topic>
    <ml:presenter>Clark Richey</ml:presenter>
  </ml:details>
</ml:Event>
