<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ml:Event status="Published" user-group="nymug" xmlns:ml="http://developer.marklogic.com/site/internal" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <ml:title>Development and Deployment of Enterprise-Scale MarkLogic Solutions</ml:title>
  <ml:created>2011-01-06T13:34:13.839469-08:00</ml:created>
  <ml:last-updated>2011-01-06T17:48:56.824019-08:00</ml:last-updated>
  <ml:description>
    <p><a title="Flatirons Solutions" href="http://www.flatironssolutions.com/"><img style="float: right;" title="Flatirons Solutions" src="/media/flatirons-solutions-logo.png" alt="Flatirons Solutions " width="154" height="72"/></a>Talk to a developer that is using MarkLogic  and you’ll hear about <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FLWOR">
FLOWRs</a>, XQuery patterns for faceted searching, use of  XPath vs. <a href="http://developer.marklogic.com/pubs/4.2/apidocs/SearchBuiltins.html">CTS 
functions</a> and lots of exciting ideas about how to manipulate large 
volumes of XML content. But how do you actually build, deploy and 
maintain a solution that uses all the power of MarkLogic? And deploy to 
multiple environments? With meaningful test data? Facilitating <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development">TDD</a>? And 
leveraging continuous integration technologies?  Flatirons Solutions 
consultant <a href="http://www.meetup.com/den-mark-logic/members/13145863/">Brad Rix</a> will provide an informative presentation on best 
practices used to automate the build, test and deploy cycle for 
MarkLogic applications.</p>
<p>Development teams frequently fall into 
the trap of spending too much time on developing core functionality of 
an application and skimp on the dirty details of how to enable easy unit
 testing, building and testing with clean test data, automated build and
 deployments to multiple target environments, etc. As a result of this, 
projects can frequently run afoul of a host of build, test and 
deployment issues that can drive up project costs and greatly impact the
 quality of the final solution.</p>
<p>Using the <a href="/pubs/4.2/apidocs/AdminLibrary.html">MarkLogic Admin APIs</a> 
and other open source tools, Brad has led the development of a set of 
configurable processes that dramatically reduce the time, cost and 
complexity of  the build, unit test and deploy cycle to multiple 
environments. This is the hard, dirty work of developing truly robust, 
enterprise ready applications. By automating these tasks, your project 
can focus valuable development energy on providing more functionality to
 the user without the risk of deployment complexities getting in the way
 of user adoption.     </p>
<p>The presentation will include a live 
demonstration, along with an overview of "lessons learned" while using 
these best practices in a production setting.  </p>
<p>If you're planning on coming, please kindly <a href="http://www.meetup.com/NY-MUG/calendar/15942482/">RSVP</a>, so we can bring the right amount of food and drink.  </p>
  </ml:description>
  <ml:details>
    <ml:date>2011-01-27</ml:date>
    <ml:time>6:00 PM</ml:time>
    <ml:location><a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=d&amp;hl=en&amp;saddr=&amp;daddr=1230+Avenue+of+the+Americas%2C+New+York%2C+NY+10020%2C+us">Simon &amp; Schuster Offices</a>
<br/>
1230 Avenue of the Americas, between 48th and 49th Streets on Sixth Avenue
<br/>
New York, NY 10020</ml:location>
    <ml:topic>Development and Deployment of Enterprise-Scale MarkLogic Solutions</ml:topic>
    <ml:presenter>Brad Rix</ml:presenter>
  </ml:details>
</ml:Event>
