<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ml:Announcement status="Published" user-group="" xmlns:ml="http://developer.marklogic.com/site/internal" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <ml:title>DemoJam at Balisage 2010! The Best 5 Minute Demo to Win an iPad.</ml:title>
  <ml:author>Cleo Haynal</ml:author>
  <ml:date>2010-07-13</ml:date>
  <ml:body>
    <p><img style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" title="balisage 2010" src="http://www.balisage.net/Logo/Balisage-2010-logoType.png" alt="balisage 2010" width="450" height="163"/></p>
<p> </p>
<ml:teaser>MarkLogic is an active sponsor of <a href="http://www.balisage.net">Balisage 2010</a>, which will take place on August 3-6, 2010 in Montreal, Canada.
<p>Balisage is an annual conference devoted to the theory and practice of
 descriptive markup and related technologies for structuring and 
managing information.</p>
</ml:teaser>
<p>On August 4th, at 6:30p, MarkLogic will invite conference attendees 
to participate in a demo contest at a local bar.</p>
<p>Demos must be of technical nature, may be on any topic likely to be 
of interest to the attendees at Balisage, and are the responsibility of 
the presenter. The demo length is strictly limited to 5 minutes. 
We will limit the jam to the first 10 demos that arrive first-come, first-serve starting at 6:30p.  MarkLogic will supply a Windows PC with Internet access and a USB port 
for use by presenters. </p>
<p>Presenters are also welcome to use their own laptops for the demos.</p>
<p>Judges will determine the winners through audience vote. The winner 
will go home with an iPad. Other prizes will be distributed to 
participants.</p>
<p>Bring your favorite 5 minute demo to show during our Demo Jam 
Contest. Join us at 6:30 for beer and tasty nosh; we’ll start the demos 
at 7 pm at the bar. Your conference badge is your ticket to enter. All 
Balisage participants are welcome!</p>
<p>
More info can be found at <a href="http://www.balisage.net/2010/DemoJam.html">balisage.net</a></p>
  </ml:body>
  <ml:created>2010-07-13T12:05:38.335998-07:00</ml:created>
  <ml:last-updated>2010-07-13T17:07:36.976914-07:00</ml:last-updated>
</ml:Announcement>
