<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ml:Announcement status="Published" user-group="" xmlns:ml="http://developer.marklogic.com/site/internal" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <ml:title>DemoJam at Balisage 2010 on August 4, 2010</ml:title>
  <ml:author>Cleo Haynal</ml:author>
  <ml:date>2010-08-01</ml:date>
  <ml:body>
<ml:teaser>
    <h3>Beer and Demo! </h3>
<p>What better way to finish the day at one of the world's premier XML events?</p>
</ml:teaser>
<p><img style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" title="bar" src="http://www.winniesbar.com/Karina/pictures/48-20-Stairs%20Bar.jpg" alt="bar" width="450" height="300"/></p>
<p>On August 4th, at 6:30p, MarkLogic will invite the <a href="http://www.balisage.net">Balisage</a> 2010 conference attendees 
to participate in a demo contest at the Sir Winston Churchill Pub Complex in the Karina Room.</p>
<p>The address is <a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?q=1459+rue+Crescent,+Montr%C3%A9al,&amp;oe=utf-8&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=1459+Rue+Crescent,+Montr%C3%A9al,+Communaut%C3%A9-Urbaine-de-Montr%C3%A9al,+Qu%C3%A9bec+H3G+2B2,+Canada&amp;gl=us&amp;ei=GSBVTPXFAY_0tgP5m6TZAg&amp;ved=0CBQQ8gEwAA&amp;ll=45.497759,-73.576899&amp;spn=0.003279,0.009109&amp;t=h&amp;z=17">1459 rue Crescent, Montréal</a>, and is walking distance from the conference hotel.</p>
<h3>About the contest:</h3>
<p>Demos must be of technical nature, may be on any topic likely to be 
of interest to the attendees at Balisage, and are the responsibility of 
the presenter. The demo length is strictly limited to 5 minutes. 
We will limit the jam to the first 10 demos that arrive first-come, 
first-serve starting at 6:30p.  MarkLogic will supply a Windows PC with 
Internet access and a USB port 
for use by presenters. </p>
<p>Presenters are also welcome to use their own laptops for the demos.  (Mac folks, best to bring your connectors).</p>
<p>Judges will determine the winners through audience vote. The winner gets an iPad. Other prizes will be distributed to 
participants.</p>
<p>Bring your favorite 5 minute demo to show during our Demo Jam 
Contest. Join us at 6:30 for beer and tasty nosh; we’ll start the demos 
at 7 pm at the bar. Your conference badge is your ticket to enter. All 
Balisage participants are welcome!</p>
<p>
More info can be found at <a href="http://www.balisage.net/2010/DemoJam.html">balisage.net</a></p>
  </ml:body>
  <ml:created>2010-08-01T00:50:01.538585-07:00</ml:created>
  <ml:last-updated>2010-08-01T00:41:27.504253-07:00</ml:last-updated>
</ml:Announcement>
