<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ml:Announcement status="Published" user-group="" xmlns:ml="http://developer.marklogic.com/site/internal" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <ml:title>Jason Hunter to speak at Sold Out QCon SF, November 3, 2010 </ml:title>
  <ml:author>Eric Bloch</ml:author>
  <ml:date>2010-10-27</ml:date>
  <ml:body>
    <p><a href="http://qconsf.com/"><img style="border: 1px solid black; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;" title="QCon SF 2010" src="http://qconsf.com/sf2010/file?path=/qcon-sanfran-2010/top-banner.jpg" alt="QCon SF 2010" width="600"/></a></p>
<p> </p>
<p>QCon is coming up next week here in San Francisco.   From the <a title="QCon SF 2010" href="http://qconsf.com/">conference website</a>, you can see:</p>
<p> </p>
<div>
    </div>
<blockquote>
<div><em>
<ml:teaser>
QCon is a practitioner-driven conference designed for team leads, architects and project management.  The program includes <a href="http://qconsf.com/sf2010/tutorials/">two tutorial days</a> led by industry experts and authors and <a href="http://qconsf.com/sf2010/schedule/wednesday.jsp">three conference days</a> with <a href="http://qconsf.com/sf2010/tracks/">16 tracks</a>
 covering a wide variety of relevant and exciting topics in software 
development today.   There is no other event in the US with similar 
opportunities for learning, networking, and tracking innovation 
occurring in the enterprise software development community.
</ml:teaser>
</em></div>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p>Among a really great list of speakers including folks like <a href="http://martinfowler.com/">Martin Fowler</a> (of OOP fame) and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Henry_Holmes_Ingalls,_Jr.">Dan Ingalls</a> (of Smalltalk fame), MarkLogic's own <a href="http://servlets.com/jason">Jason Hunter</a> will be speaking on our combination of search-engine and database in MarkLogic's Universal Index.  Details of his presentation are below:</p>
<p style="text-align: left; margin-top: 7px; margin-bottom: 7px;"><strong style="text-align: left;">Presentation: "Unifying the Search Engine and NoSQL DBMS with a Universal Index"</strong>
</p>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<div style="text-align: left; margin-top: 5px;"><strong style="text-align: left;">Track:</strong><span class="Apple-converted-space"> </span><a class="textlink" style="text-align: left; text-decoration: none;" href="http://qconsf.com/sf2010/tracks/show_track.jsp?trackOID=412">Solutions Track: Wednesday, November 3rd</a></div>
<p style="text-align: left; margin-top: 7px; margin-bottom: 7px;"><strong style="text-align: left;">Time:</strong><span class="Apple-converted-space"> </span>Wednesday 12:05 - 13:05</p>
<p style="text-align: left; margin-top: 7px; margin-bottom: 7px;"><strong style="text-align: left;">Location:</strong><span class="Apple-converted-space"> </span>Concordia Room</p>
<div style="text-align: left;"><strong style="text-align: left;">Abstract:</strong></div>
<div style="text-align: left;">
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">
In contrast to single-function architectures, MarkLogic Server takes an
unusual approach to collapsing the usual hierarchies of types of servers
that make up a complete application, combining Search, a NoSQL DBMS, and an
application server in a single kernel. The computational foundation for
this hybrid is the Universal Index.
</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">
In this talk, we'll begin with the familiar text indexing data structures
and algorithms that underlie search engine technologies. We'll extend that
index to cover document structure and semantics, add scalar range indexing
in one and two dimensions (including geospatial application), and then
incorporate "reverse" indexing of queries. We will demonstrate a novel type
of "matchmaking" query whose evaluation is based on a composition of
forward and reverse index evaluation. Finally, we'll explore the means by
which all of this indexing may efficiently run concurrently with querying,
using Multi-Version Concurrency Control and Log-Structured Merge Trees,
providing ACID transactions together with lock-free query evaluation,
built-in sharding, terabyte-per-server scale-out, replication, and query
distribution.
</p>
</div>
</div>
  </ml:body>
  <ml:created>2010-10-27T10:35:35.437705-07:00</ml:created>
  <ml:last-updated>2010-10-27T11:42:25.734587-07:00</ml:last-updated>
</ml:Announcement>
